So good, so we can finally get underway, so
this is CS 6700 reinforcement learning, if
anyone is here by mistake looking for the
planning class still well you should leave
okay, and yeah so how many of you were in
the machine learning course just for me to
get a sense large fraction of the people were
enable and so, this is a very the different
kind of learning than what we looked at it
am I right?
So in machine learning we looked at familiar
modes of machine learning where the idea was
to learn from data, you know so you had given
lot of data as training instances for you
and essentially we're trying to learn from
those training instances as to what to do
right.
.
And there were different kinds of problems
that we are looking at, so one was supervised
learning problem in which you are looking
at classification and regression, oh yeah
so in the machine learning class we looked
at learning from data right primarily so one
of the models we looked at was supervised
learning it where we learnt about classification
and regression the goal there was to learning
from an input space to a output which could
be a categorical output in which case in classification
could be a continuous output in which case
it was called regression right.
So if you haven't been in the ml class don't
worry about it right because this is just
to tell you that our RL is not what we learnt
in the ML class okay.
So she hasn’t learned anything in the ML
class then you don't have anything to unlearn.
So don't worry so the second per second kind
of learning thing we looked at was unsupervised
learning where there was really no output
that was expected of you right since therefore
there was no supervision the goal was to find
patterns in the input data.
I will give you lot of data points you can
you find out if there are groupings of similar
kinds of data points can i divided them into
segments right.
So that kind of a thing was called clustering,
right or you are asked to figure out if there
were frequently repeating patterns in the
data right and so this is called frequent
pattern mining or derived problem there was
Association rule mining and so on so forth
right so people have heard me give this analogy
multiple, multiple times before but this is
the most apt one how did you learn to cycle,
right.
so was it supervised learning so how did you
learn to cycle, somebody who hasn't heard
me or then who hasn't been in ML, you haven't
been in ML right okay, how did you learn to
cycle, was did somebody tell you how to cycle
and then you just followed their instruction?
Okay first of all tell you know how to cycle?
Yes.
Do you know how to cycle, yeah you?
Okay how did you learn to cycle fell down
a couple of times and that automatic you made
cycle, you have to actually figure out how
to not default down, right.
So falling down alone is not enough but you
have to try different things right it's not
supervised learning is really not supervised
learning how much everything because, now
that I have given this talk multiple times
people are getting wise to it, right earlier
when I used to ask these people uses of course
in supervised learning mantle was there holding
me or my father was telling me what to do
and so on so forth.
At best what did they tell you, hey look out
look out don't fall down, right.
So that doesn't count our supervision, so
or keep your body right keep your body up
or something some kind of very vague instructions
was what they're giving you right, supervised
learning would mean that so we get on the
cycle somebody tells you okay, now push down
with your left foot with three pounds of pressure
right and move your center of gravity three
degrees to the right, right.
So this is I mean somebody has to give you
exactly what is the control signals that you
have to give to your body in order for you
to cycle right, then that would be supervised
learning.
If somebody actually gives you supervision
in that scale you would probably have never
learned to cycle we think about it because
it's such a complex, complex dynamical system
if somebody gives you control at that level
gives you input at that level you will never
learn to cycle.
And so immediately people flip and say that
it was unsupervised learning right, because
here of course nobody told me how to cycle
therefore it is unsupervised learning.
So if it is truly unsupervised learning what
should have happened is you should have watched
hundreds of videos of people cycling figure
out what is the pattern of cycling that they
do okay, and get on a cycle and reproducing
right.
So that is essentially what unsupervised learning
would be you just have lot of data right and
based on the data I figure out what the patterns
are and then you try to execute those patterns
that does not work right, you can watch hours
and hours of somebody playing fly simulator
you cannot go and fly a plane wait, so you
have to get on the cycle yourself and you
have to try things yourself right so that
that's the crux here right.
So what it's its how do you learn to cycle
is neither of the above right is neither supervised
nor and supervised it's an it's a different
paradigm.
So the reason I always start out my talks
not just in the class but in gender when I
talk about reinforcement learning is because
people will always talk about reinforcement
learning and unsupervised learning and it's
always really irks me because it's not an
unsupervised learning just because you don't
have a classification error or a class label
doesn't make it unsupervised learning it is
a completely different form of learning and
so reinforcement learning is essentially this
mathematical formulas for this trial and error
kind of learning right.
So how do you learn from this kind of minimal
feedback you know, falling down hurts or somebody
your mom or somebody stands there and claps,
when you finally managed to get on the cycle
you know that's kind of a positive reinforcement.
Where did he fall down you get hurt right,
that's kind of a negative feedback how do
you just use this kinds of minimal feedback
and you learn to cycle then, so this is essentially
the crux of what reinforcement learning is
about trial and error right.
So the goal here is to learn about a system
through interacting with the system right
it's not something that is done completely
offline okay you have some notion of interaction
with the system okay and you learn about the
system through that interaction.
Reinforcement learning originally was inspired
by behavioral psychology right.
.
So one of the earliest reinforcement systems
that were said he was a Pavlov's dog, how
many of you know of the Pavlov's dog experiment?
what is the Pavlov's dog experiment in association
with whenever he's going to do okay, so whenever
like he just utterly need above the dog started
expecting the food and started salivating
yeah so that is called a condition perfect,
so when the dog looks at the food and start
salivating it is a primary response because
that is a reason for it to salivate on the
site of food in any idea why?
Exactly so it is preparing to digest the food
you know and then show the food is preparing
to digest the food so it starts salivating
right.
So then now if you think about it right hearing
the bell and it celebrates what is it doing
preparing to digest a bell?
So when you ring the bell and then serve the
food the dog forms an association between
the bell and the food right and later on when
you just ring the bell without even giving
the food the dog starts salivating in response
to digesting the food that it expects to be
delivered right so essentially the food is
the payoff you know the food is like the reward
for it and it has learned to form associations
between signals in this case which was a bell
like an input signal which was the bell and
the reward that is going to get right.
So this was called behavioral conditioning
right and so inspired by these kinds of experiments
on the more complex behavioral experiments
on animals and people started to come up with
different theories to explain how learning
proceeds right.
In fact some of the earlier reinforcement
learning papers appeared in behavioral psychology
journals right, the earliest paper by Sutton
and Border appeared in brain and behavioral
sciences Journal, just go back I needed to
need to say something about Sutton- Border
know that there's a larger audience you can
tell that what then so the we're going to
follow a textbook written by Richardson and
Andy border right but more importantly they
are also kind of the co-founders of the modern
field of reinforcement learning right.
So in 1983 they wrote a paper adaptive neuron
like element that learn control behavior from
something to that effect right and that essentially
kick started this whole modern field of reinforcement
learning.
So the concept of reinforcement learning like
I said goes back to Pavlov and earlier right,
people have been talking about those kind
of behavioral conditioning and learning and
sure, but the whole modern computational techniques
that people use in reinforcement learning
are started by Sutton and border.
So what is reinforcement learning right, so
it's learning about stimuli right the inputs
that are coming to you and the actions that
you can take in response to it right, learning
about the stimuli only from rewards and punishments
so you're not going to get anything else food
is a reward right falling down and scraping
your hand there's a punishment, right.
.
So only from these kinds of rewards and punishments
alone right, there is no detailed supervision
available nobody tells you what is the response
that you should give to a specific input right,
suppose you are playing a game there are multiple
ways in which you can learn to play a game
right so we can learn to play chess by looking
at a board position right and then looking
at a table that tells you for this board position
this is the move you have to make right and
then you go and make the move alright.
So that is a kind of supervision that you
could get you know that gives you a kind of
a mapping from the input to the output right,
it gives you a mapping from the input to the
output and essentially you learn to generalize
from that.
So this is what we mean by detailed supervision
so, another way of learning to play chess
is just you have an open-ended sit in front
of him and you just make a sequence of moves
at the end of the move you win okay, you get
a reward make somebody pays you say 10 rupees,
okay if you lose you how to pay the opponent
and ten rupees that's all, that’s all that
happens is all the feedback you’re going
to get right, whether you are going to get
the 10 rupees or going to lose the 10 rupees
at the end of the game so nobody tells you
given this position this is the move you should
have made that is what we mean by saying learning
from rewards and punishments in the absence
of detailed supervision is that clear okay?
And the crucial component to this is trial
and error learning because since I don't know
what is the right thing to do given an input
right I need to try multiple things to see
what the outcome will be right, I need to
try different things to see if I am going
to get the reward or not right if I don't
try different things, I'm not going to be
able to learn anything at all right.
So we will I can give you more formal mathematical
reasons for why we need all of this as we
let go on but this is intuitively you can
understand this as a requiring exploration
so, that you know what the right outcome is
right.
And there are a bunch of things which are
also characteristic of reinforcement learning
problems one of those is that the outcomes
right they paid the rewards and punishments
based on which you are learning can be fairly
delayed in time they need not be temporarily
close to the thing that cost it, I mean while
you are playing a game let us say right, so
you might you know drop a batsman right and
then he goes on to score like 150 or something
like that right so then you lose the match
at the end of the day right but even that
cost you to lose the match is the dropped
catch that probably happened around the 12th
over right, or it could be much more convoluted
causal cause and effect right so and how many
of you follow cricket?
My god really losing popularity, put your
hands down, I'm not going to give a cricket
example then forget it okay so a bunch of
other things right so, so we talked about
delayed rewards the rewards could come much
later in time from the action that cost the
reward will happen right for example, let's
go back to our cycling case that I might have
done something stupid honoring all I might
have gone over a stone somewhere right, while
I am cycling at a very high speed and might
have been a small stone in this the road and
that that will cause me to lose my balance
right.
And then I will try my level best to get the
balance back right I might not and I will
finally fall down and get her that doesn't
mean what caused the falling down is the last
action I tried right, I might have desperately
tried to jump off the cycle or something like
that but that is not what caused the punishment
right, the what caused the punishment happened
a few seconds ago when I ran over the stone,
right.
So there could be this kind of a temporal
disconnect between what causes the punishment
from the actual reward and punishment so it
becomes a little tricky how do you are going
to learn those things like learn the association's
right.
So quite often write your wind need a sequence
of actions to obtain a reward and it's not
going to be like a one-shot thing they're
going to need a sequence of actions, so again
going back to the chess example right, you
are not going to get a reward every time we
move a piece on the board right, you have
to finish playing the game at the end of the
game if you actually manage to when you get
a reward so, it is a sequence of actions right.
And therefore you need to learn some kind
of an association between the inputs that
you are seeing in this case it will be both
positions right or how fast the cycle is moving
and how unbalanced do you feel and so on so
forth right to actions so the inputs that
you are getting which sometimes which we will
call states right and the actions that you
take in response to this input that you are
seeing right.
So this is essentially what you are going
to be doing when you are solving a reinforcement
learning problem.
So this kind of associations is essentially
called as policies right, so what you are
essentially learning is a policy to behave
in a world, right.
So learning a policy to play chess or you
are learning a policy to cycle right so this
is essentially what you are learning that
you are not just learning about individual
actions right, and all of this happen typically
in a noisy stochastic world that the mix things
more challenging, so these are all the different
characteristics of reinforcement learning
problems right and I will be looking at all
of this as we go along in when this not be
explicitly talking about each and every one
of these bullet points but everything that
we look at all the algorithms all the methods
that we look at as we go along in this course
okay, we'll have all these aspects as part
of it okay.
.
So reinforcement learning has been used fairly
successfully in a wide variety of applications
right, so you can see a helicopter there okay,
so that is not a cut and paste error the helicopter
is actually flying upside down, so the this
group at Stanford and Berkeley which have
actually use reinforcement learning to trainer
after to fly all kinds of things not just
upside down an aural agent can do all kinds
of tricks on the helicopter so, I will show
you a video in a minute and it is an amazing
piece of work night I mean it's considered
it was considered the showpiece application
for reinforcement learning getting such a
complex control system to work and it actually
could do things at a much finer levels of
control than a human being could.
Relax after all a machine so we would expect
that but the tricky part was how it learn
to control this complex system from without
any human intervention right, and in the middle
right so they I have a couple of games there
so that is can you see that is too small an
arrow that's a game called backgammon right
so how many of you know about backgammon,
1, 2 plus one maybe.
How many of you know about Ludo?
Okay fine so backgammon is like a two player
oh okay so you throw the dice you move pieces
around and you take them off the board right,
so it's a fairly easy game but then you have
all kinds of strategies that you could do
with it but it's also a hard game for computers
to play because of the stochasticity right
and also because of a large branching factor
that is that in the game, so a teach point
there are many combinations in which you could
move the board pieces around and then there
is die role that adds an additional complexity.
So people are not really you know getting
great results and then there's this person
Jerry tesaro from IBM who came up with something
called neuro gammon thing was called neuro
gammon and that was trained using supervised
learning and the neural network and, so if
it had if he had done it recently it would
have been called a deep learning version of
neuro gamma or something because he did it
back in the 90s early 90s it was just called
neural network question of backgammon and
I played really well for a computer program
right so it was essentially the best computer
program backgammon player at that point.
And then Jerry heard about TDI we heard about
reinforcement learning he decided to train
a reinforcement learning agent to play backgammon
so what he did was set up this reinforcement
learning agent which played against another
copy of itself, let them play hundreds and
hundreds of games rather thousands and thousands
of games so essentially what they did was
so you train one copy for like 100 games or
something then you move it here right freeze
it and then continue learning with this.
So essentially what was happening as you learn
you are playing against better and better
place gradually your opponent was also improving
right.
And then so this was called self play right,
so he trained the backgammon using self play
and he came to a point where they TD gammon
as he called it was even better than the human
player of backgammon at that point in the
world right so they actually had head-to-head
the challenge with the human champion that
is a world championship of backgammon you
know it's apparently very popular in the Middle
East and people actually have World Championships
that's the world championship of backgammon
and so, he challenged the human champion which
IBM seems to do a lot right i mean they challenged
a caspero matches and things like this so,
he also challenged just this out of work for
IBM.
You should realize right people who spend
a lot of resources getting computers to play
games, I will probably be working for IBM
so, Jerry had this thing and it beat the world
champion so we have reinforcement learning
agent that's the best backgammon player in
the world not no more best computer player
or anything right so we could actually make
that game right and there's another game that
this is a snapshot from the game of Go right
so people have let go, oh come on if that
leaves one or two people who have played go
okay, people have played the hotel oh okay
that's not a very few number isn't it one
of those free games on ubuntu I thought everybody
plays that because I mean at some point or
other well you would rather play Othello then
watch paint dry you know.
But anyway it goes a like a more complex version
of Othello few with right it's again a very
hard game for computers to play because the
branching factor is huge right and it is actually
a miracle that humans even play this because
the search trees and other things that's really
complex right so this is 11 case which clearly
illustrates that humans actually solve problems
in a fundamentally different way then we try
to write down in our algorithms because, they
seem to be making all kinds of intuitive leaps
in order to be able to play go right.
So there's this person David silver who currently
works for Google deep mind and but before
that he spent some time with Jerry tesoro
at IBM and at some point along the way he
came up with this reinforcement learning agent
called the TD search that place go at a decent
level still not, not like master human level
performance but it performs plays at a pretty
decent level ok so he what I'm pointing out
here is things that are typically hard for
traditional computer algorithms or even traditional
machine learning approaches to solve a as
had good success right.
And here is another example of them to point
emphasis this or that I forget which one right,
they told me I should use only one of those
screens for pointing because it's hard for
them to record on the other one I forget which
one okay, forget it there are some robots
on the bottom left of the screen right and
so that is a snapshot from the UT Austin Robo
soccer team called Austin Villa right, and
they usually first we're learning to get their
robots to execute really complex strategies
so this is really cool.
But the nice thing about the Robo socket application
is that they don't use reinforcement learning
alone right they actually use a mix of different
learning strategies and also planning and
so on so forth, which is going on the other
studio right so they use a mix of different
kinds of AI and machine learning techniques
in order to get a very very competent agent
is very hard to beat and they I mean the Champions
I think two or three years running now in
the humanoid league right.
And again hard control problems things like
how do I take a spot-kick, you know those
were the things for which they used reinforcement
learning which is a really hard balancing
products we basically have to balance the
robot on one leg and then swing the other
leg so that you can take the kick and it turns
out to be a hard control problem right.
So they used RL to order to solve those right
and then up on the top right ok is an application
which will probably the one that actually
makes money of all these three all the others
right that is on essentially on using read
first learning to solve online learning right.
So online learning is a use case where I do
not get I don't have the feedback available
to me a priori right, so the feedback keeps
coming piecemeal right so for example that
is a case where we are having new stories
that need to be shown to people that come
to me webpage right, and when people come
to the page I will have like some editors
will pick like 20 stories for mean d from
those 20 stories i have to figure out which
are the ones i put up there prominent and
what is the feedback i am going again.
Nobody tells me what stories that user is
going to like I mean then I cannot have a
supervised learning algorithm here right.
So the feedback I am going to get this if
the user clicks on the story i am going to
get a reward the user does not click on the
story I will not get a reward that's, essentially
the feedback i am going to get nobody tells
me anything beforehand.
So i have to try out things i have to show
different stories to figure out which one
is going to click on and i have very few attempts
to do this in so how do I do this more effectively
so, people have done a supervisor approach
for solving this and it has worked fairly
successfully.
So it has worked fairly successfully but what
reinforcement seems to be a much more in a
natural way of modeling these problems.
So not only in these kinds of a new story
selection people use reinforcement ending
ideas even in ad selection right, so how do
I see some of those ads that you see on the
sides when you go to Google or some other
page right so how are those ads selected so,
so there might be some very basic economic
criterion for selecting a slate of ads okay,
here are these 10 ads which would probably
give me the right payoff right and then you
can figure out which of those which three
of those 10am I going to put here and things
like that you could use a reinforcement learning
solution for selecting those right.
.
Of course the this is this whole field called
computational advertising right, it is a lot
more complex than what I explained but RL
is a component in computational brutalizing
as well right.
okay here is the video courtesy Andrews webpage
the people recognized again there huh, okay
which is not a human-sized helicopter but
still it is a fairly large amazing all of
this is being done by a aural agent this goes
on for a while we stop.